<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Band Brothers Save Tool</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006, 2007 Matt Behrens</year>
    </copyright>

    <author>
      <firstname>Matt</firstname>

      <surname>Behrens</surname>

      <email>matt@zigg.com</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>A few quick thanks to various folks for making this whole thing
    possible:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://jubai.sakura.ne.jp/jubai/bandbrothers/">OUT
        TAKE ENSEMBLE</ulink>, home of the original Band Brothers Music
        Editor, for inspiring me to create this tool;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The guys behind <ulink
        url="http://www.python.org/">Python</ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://www.wxwidgets.org/">wxWidgets</ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://www.wxpython.org/">wxPython</ulink>, and <ulink
        url="http://wxglade.sourceforge.net/">wxGlade</ulink>, for making it
        relatively easy for me to put a nice user-friendly face on the whole
        project;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The apparently soon-to-be-reborn <ulink
        url="http://ndsart.net/">NDSart</ulink>, for carrying the torch of
        creativity in gaming, letting me know of OUT TAKE ENSEMBLE in the
        first place, and hooking me up with my first guinea pigs;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>And of course, <ulink
        url="http://www.nintendo.co.jp/">Nintendo</ulink>, for taking a chance
        on Daigasso! Band Brothers in the first place and giving me my
        number-one reason to own a Nintendo DS for many, many months. (Now,
        Nintendo of America, where's our American version?)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the Save Tool</title>

    <para>The Band Brothers Save Tool imports and exports songs created in the
    Nintendo DS game Daigasso! Band Brothers so that they may be exchanged
    with far-away users.</para>

    <para>The tool currently supports the following methods of getting access
    to the save data for the game, which contains the saved songs:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Datel Ltd.'s Action Replay MAX for GBA/DS</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GBA Movie Player M3</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Any other method supporting a save dump (<xref
        linkend="save-dump" />)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Installation</title>

      <section>
        <title>Microsoft Windows</title>

        <para>Precompiled binaries are offered for Microsoft Windows. Simply
        unzip all files into their own directory; there are quite a few, so
        keep them separate from other programs so you can easily delete the
        software at a later date.</para>

        <para>To run the save tool, double-click
        <filename>bbstool.exe</filename>.</para>

        <para>If you don't wish to use the binaries, you can use the
        platform-neutral method as well (<xref
        linkend="other-platforms" />).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="other-platforms">
        <title>Other Platforms</title>

        <para>The save tool is written in the Python language and uses the
        wxPython GUI toolkit. You will need the following dependencies
        installed on your computer:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.python.org/">Python</ulink>
            2.4</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.wxpython.org/">wxPython</ulink> 2.6
            (Unicode version on Microsoft Windows)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Once you've installed these on your system, run the
        <filename>bbstool.py</filename> script to start the save tool.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Accessing Your Game Save</title>

      <section>
        <title>Action Replay MAX</title>

        <para>The save tool is designed to work with the 1.04 firmware
        revision and above. If you have an older Action Replay MAX, get the
        upgrade (version 1.06 is recommended) from <ulink
        url="http://us.codejunkies.com/support_home.asp">Datel's support
        site</ulink>; it will speed up your transfers by a factor of four or
        more and make your use of the save tool less painful<footnote>
            <para>The first release of the save tool was developed using the
            old Action Replay MAX firmware. Save transfers using this method
            took <emphasis>8-9 minutes</emphasis> using this method, each way;
            you could expect to spend 20 minutes just to try one new
            song.</para>
          </footnote>.</para>

        <para>To get your save in a format usable by the save tool:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Follow the procedures in your Action Replay MAX manual to
            back up the save to your PC Database.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>The save tool works only with uncompressed saves, so you
            must uncompress your save. From the Action Replay software on your
            PC, select <guimenuitem>Max Drive DS (DS)</guimenuitem>,
            <guimenuitem>Manage and swap saves</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>My
            MaxDrive Vault</guimenuitem>. (You do not need to connect your
            Action Replay MAX as long as your save is already on your
            PC.)</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select the save you want to modify on the left and select
            the decompress and export button, which looks like an open vise
            with an arrow pointing to the left.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select a directory to uncompress the save to and select
            <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The resulting file will be named
            whatever your save was titled with a <filename>.duc</filename>
            extension. This file is usable with the save tool.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>If you don't choose to upgrade your Action Replay MAX, you will
        have to find and copy your save file from the <filename>\Program
        Files\Datel\Nintendo DS - GBA Max Drive\PC</filename> directory and
        rename it so it carries a <filename>.duc</filename> extension.</para>

        <para>You are now ready to load your save into the save tool (<xref
        linkend="loading-data" />).</para>

        <para>Once you're done working with your save and have saved it to a
        save file (<xref linkend="saving-data" />), you need to copy it back
        to your game card:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>From the Action Replay software on your PC, select
            <guimenuitem>Max Drive DS (DS)</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Manage
            and swap saves</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>My MaxDrive
            Vault</guimenuitem>.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select the compress and import button, which looks like a
            closed vise with an arrow pointing downward.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select the save file you modified with the tool.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Follow the procedures in your Action Replay MAX manual to
            copy the newly edited save back to your game card.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>Again, if you haven't upgraded your Action Replay MAX, you will
        have to rename the edited file back to the correct extension and put
        it into the <filename>\Program Files\Datel\Nintendo DS - GBA Max
        Drive\PC</filename> directory before copying the save back to your
        game card.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>GBA Movie Player M3</title>

        <para>If you are playing your game from your GBA Movie Player M3
        instead of from your original game card, the M3 will store your game
        save on the CompactFlash or Secure Digital memory card you use as its
        storage card.</para>

        <para>The save tool can open these directly on the card and write them
        back out in the same manner. When you are ready to load your data
        (<xref linkend="loading-data" />) into the tool, you can find the
        <filename>.dat</filename> file that the M3 generates in the
        <filename>ndssave</filename> folder on your storage card.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="save-dump">
        <title>Save dump</title>

        <para>The save tool can also use a save dump, which is simply a file
        containing the contents of the save EEPROM on the game card. Such a
        file will be either exactly 262,144 bytes in length or be longer with
        padding at the end, and by tradition is named with a
        <filename>.sav</filename> extension. (The save tool will detect
        trailing padding in this mode and preserve it.)</para>

        <para>If you have a homebrew-capable Nintendo DS, you can use <ulink
        url="http://www.pat.hi-ho.ne.jp/sata68/nds.shtml#rain">Rain</ulink>,
        which will, when booted in a Nintendo DS with the Daigasso! Band
        Brothers game card inserted, allow you to back up and restore the game
        save to one of several places, including the filesystem on a CF-based
        M3. Once you've done this, you can connect the storage card to your
        computer and load your data (<xref linkend="loading-data" />) directly
        from the storage card.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using the Save Tool</title>

      <section id="loading-data">
        <title>Opening Save Data</title>

        <para>Once you've gained access to your save data from your PC,
        opening it is straightforward:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>From the <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu> menu, select
            <guisubmenu><accel>O</accel>pen</guisubmenu>, and select the type
            of save file you are opening.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the save file you want to open from the file
            dialog.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>If the file loads successfully, you will see the titles of your
        songs appear in the main window. Slots that do not appear to contain a
        valid song will read <guilabel>(Empty or invalid)</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>The save tool will do checks on the save file to make sure it is
        precisely what it expects before permitting you to manipulate it. If
        it isn't, you'll get one of several errors. If you get one and you're
        sure your file is intact, contact me.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Importing Songs</title>

        <para>The save tool lets you import the contents of a
        <filename>.bbs</filename> file, which contains a Daigasso! Band
        Brothers score, into one of the eight slots in your save. If the slot
        you want to use contains a song you want to keep, you should export
        that song first (<xref linkend="exporting-songs" />).</para>

        <para>To import a song:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Select the slot you want to import the song into from the
            list of songs.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select
            <guibutton><accel>I</accel>mport...</guibutton></para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the <filename>.bbs</filename> file you want to
            import.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>If successful, the title of the song in the slot you selected
        will be replaced with the title of the song you imported.</para>

        <para>The save tool will do checks on the score file to make sure it
        is indeed a valid score file before importing it into your save. If it
        isn't, you'll get one of several errors. If you get one and you're
        sure your file is intact, contact me.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="exporting-songs">
        <title>Exporting Songs</title>

        <para>You can share songs you created by exporting them to
        <filename>.bbs</filename> files. This procedure will make a copy of
        the song in the slot you select and create a .bbs file that you can
        not only share with other users of the save tool but also users of
        some other Band Brothers save manipulation tools (mostly
        Japanese).</para>

        <para>To export a song:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Select the slot that contains the song you want to import
            from the list of songs.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Select
            <guibutton><accel>E</accel>xport...</guibutton></para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find a folder to save your <filename>.bbs</filename> file
            to, give it a name, and save it.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Send your file to whomever you want to share it with.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Exporting and Importing Game Data</title>

        <para>The save tool also lets you export and import the game data
        block into and from <filename>.bbd</filename> files. The game data
        block contains your scores you've earned for each song, your personal
        information and settings, as well as what bonus songs and modes you've
        unlocked.</para>

        <para>The <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/dbbsed/">SourceForge project
        page</ulink> for the save tool has a game data package available for
        download that contains game data blocks for several permutations of
        unlocked game modes; importing these will erase your scores, personal
        information, and settings but will allow you to play modes and bonus
        songs you couldn't otherwise get to for whatever reason<footnote>
            <para>For example, Abarenbō Shōgun Theme and Gmen'75 require you
            to play the game in multiplayer mode; this requires a second
            Nintendo DS system and may not be accessible to some players. The
            Barbara Bat Theme requires you to complete Recording Ticket Level
            5 in Pro mode, which is simply beyond the finger capacity of some
            people.</para>
          </footnote>.</para>

        <para>To export your game data:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>From the <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu> menu, choose
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>xport Game
            Data...</guimenuitem></para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find a folder to save your <filename>.bbd</filename> file
            to, give it a name, and save it.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>Importing game data is similarly straightforward:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>From the File menu, choose Import Game Data...</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the <filename>.bbd</filename> file you wish to
            import.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>The save tool will do checks on the game data file to make sure
        it is indeed a valid game data file before importing it into your
        save. If it isn't, you'll get one of several errors. If you get one
        and you're sure your file is intact, contact me.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rearranging Songs</title>

        <para>If you would like to keep your songs in a particular order, such
        as your own compositions on top and imported songs on the bottom, the
        save tool can help you here as well. Once you've loaded a save file,
        you can rearrange songs simply by selecting them and using the
        <guibutton>Move <accel>U</accel>p</guibutton> and <guibutton>Move
        <accel>D</accel>own</guibutton> buttons.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="saving-data">
        <title>Saving Save Data</title>

        <para>Once you've done everything you wish to do to your save, you
        need to save it back out so you can transfer it back into your
        game.</para>

        <caution>
          <para>Before you save, it's an excellent idea to make a backup of
          your original save file. Although the save tool performs many checks
          on the data, it's still entirely possible that your save file might
          be corrupted in some novel way by either the transfer process or by
          the save tool itself. If you have a backup, you can at least go back
          to the point you were at before you started using the tool if
          something goes wrong.</para>
        </caution>

        <para>If you want to overwrite your original save file, simply choose
        <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>ave</guimenuitem> from the
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu> menu.</para>

        <para>If you want to save your changed save to a new file:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>From the <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu> menu, select
            <guimenuitem>Save <accel>A</accel>s...</guimenuitem></para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find a folder to save your save file to, give it a new name,
            and save it.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unexplained Problems</title>

      <para>Most common errors will pop up a dialog explaining the error, and
      most will happen when you're opening or saving a save file, score, or
      game data file. If you can't make sense of it, and are sure you're using
      the tool correctly, please contact me.</para>

      <para>Other errors, which I didn't anticipate, can cause the save tool
      to behave in unexplained ways. If you get one of these, please find the
      <filename>debug.txt</filename> file in the directory you started the
      save tool from. If it's not empty, it probably contains valuable
      information for me in tracking down your problem, so please send it
      along with any bug reports. It would be ideal if you could delete or
      move the file out of the way, reproduce the problem, and then send it
      along, just in case it's accumulated confusing information from previous
      problems you've had.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Developing the Save Tool</title>

    <warning>
      <para>End-users: read no further. This chapter only contains information
      for the types of people who would like to add capabilities or fix bugs
      in the save tool. If this doesn't sound like your idea of a fun evening,
      put the book down and walk away slowly.</para>
    </warning>

    <section>
      <title>Getting Into the Code</title>

      <para>The save tool is written in the Python programming language, using
      the wxPython toolkit (which is actually wxWidgets), and should run on
      any platfom that both of these exist on.</para>

      <para>Beyond these two items, you'll need one more thing, if you plan on
      modifying the GUI in any way: wxGlade. wxGlade is a GUI builder for
      wxWidgets, and is used exclusively to build the save tool's user
      interface. Please take the time to learn how wxGlade works; code can
      only be written outside of the generated sections in the main
      application (these are delimited with <code># begin wxGlade</code> and
      <code># end wxGlade</code>). If you write code inside these sections, it
      will be clobbered next time wxGlade is used to update the GUI.</para>

      <para>If you have any questions not covered here, please contact
      me.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Wish List</title>

      <para>Here's a short list of things I'd like to add to the save tool
      sometime. Some I even know how to do, but other pressures keep me from
      doing them. If you'd like to try your hand at one or more, feel free.
      You may want to ask me first to see if I've got any work-in-progress on
      them, though.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allow the end-user to modify the save name for Action Replay
          MAX save files. Currently, importing a .duc file will cause a
          duplicate entry to appear because the name in the Action Replay
          software comes from an internal name rather than the file name. This
          save name is already accessible but needs to be hooked up with UI,
          preferably on the main window.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Determine which of the sections in the game data block is the
          latest one (the game writes game data with a counter over one of
          several positions in the game data block, to lengthen the EEPROM's
          life as well as give some safety to the writing process). This
          enables a few things:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Display the game data's user name in the main
              window.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Display the player's scores for each song in a separate
              dialog. Maybe even offer an export-to-HTML option.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Some error handling that's better than
          <filename>debug.txt</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
